A Guide to the Papers of James Madison, ca. 1765-1836
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Madison ca. 1765-1836
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
: Various
ca. 328 items (3 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired through gift and purchase, ca. 1930-present.
Alternative Form Available
Digital images of this collection are available. Request images at: http://www.lib.virginia.edu/rmds/services/requests/index.html
Biographical/Historical Information
Fourth President of the United States, 1809-1817. Born March 16, 1751 in Port Conway, King George, Virginia. Died June 28, 1836 in Montpelier in Virginia. Married to Dolley Payne Todd Madison.
James Madison was brought up in Orange County, Virginia, and attended the College of New Jersey (now Princeton University). A student of history and government, well-read in law, he participated in the framing of the Virginia Constitution in 1776, served in the Continental Congress, and was a leader in the Virginia General Assembly.
When delegates to the Constitutional Convention assembled at Philadelphia, the 36-year-old Madison took frequent and emphatic part in the debates. Madison made a major contribution to the ratification of the Constitution by writing, with Alexander Hamilton and John Jay, the Federalist essays. In later years, when he was referred to as the "Father of the Constitution," Madison protested that the document was not "the off-spring of a single brain," but "the work of many heads and many hands."
In Congress, he helped frame the Bill of Rights and enact the first revenue legislation. Out of his leadership in opposition to Hamilton's financial proposals, which he felt would unduly bestow wealth and power upon northern financiers came the development of the Republican, or Jeffersonian, Party.
As President Jefferson's Secretary of State, Madison protested to warring France and Britain that their seizure of American ships was contrary to international law. The protests, John Randolph acidly commented, had the effect of "a shilling pamphlet hurled against eight hundred ships of war." Despite the unpopular Embargo Act of 1807, which did not make the belligerent nations change their ways but did cause a depression in the United States, Madison was elected President in 1808. Before he took office the Embargo Act was repealed.
During the first year of Madison's Administration, the United States prohibited trade with both Britain and France; then in May, 1810, Congress authorized trade with both, directing the President, if either would accept America's view of neutral rights, to forbid trade with the other nation. Napoleon pretended to comply. Late in 1810, Madison proclaimed non-intercourse with Great Britain. In Congress a young group including Henry Clay and John C. Calhoun, the "War Hawks," pressed the President for a more militant policy.
The British impressment of American seamen and the seizure of cargoes impelled Madison to give in to the pressure. On June 1, 1812, he asked Congress to declare war. The young Nation was not prepared to fight; its forces took a severe trouncing. The British entered Washington and set fire to the White House and the Capitol. But a few notable naval and military victories, climaxed by Gen. Andrew Jackson's triumph at New Orleans, convinced Americans that the War of 1812 had been gloriously successful. An upsurge of nationalism resulted. The New England Federalists who had opposed the war--and who had even talked secession-- were so thoroughly repudiated that Federalism disappeared as a national party.
In retirement at Montpelier, his estate in Orange County, Virginia, Madison spoke out against the disruptive states' rights influences that by the 1830's threatened to shatter the Federal Union. In a note opened after his death in 1836, he stated, "The advice nearest to my heart and deepest in my convictions is that the Union of the States be cherished and perpetuated."
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 328 items; chiefly correspondence of James Madison.
Contents List
- Land survey by James Madison, Sr. ca. [1765 February 16], ADS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #2469
- Indenture 1770 August 23, ADS, 1 p.; docketed; endorsed by George Taylor, County Clerk; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #38-144
- Harry Beverly to James Maddison [sic] 1778 September 19, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #8807-a
- James Madison to Joseph Jones [1780 December 5], ALS fragment, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box 1)
  #2988
- James Madison et. al. to [Gov. B. Harrison] 1782 April 17, LS, 2 pp. on 1 l (Box 1)
  #8991
- James Madison and Theodorick Bland to Governor Benjamin Harrison 1782 May 14, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l.; with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #2019
- Arthur Lee to James Madison 1782 May 16, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #3153
- James Madison to [?] Edmund Pendleton 1782 August 6, ALS, 1p; photocopy. (Box 1)
  #712-a
- James Madison to Auditors of Virginia 1782 August 20, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  James Madison addresses balance due to him for his service in the Virginia Assembly. #1714-a
- James Madison to Samuel House 1784 May 29, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed; silked. (Box 1)
  James Madison discusses the death of "Mr. Trist" and requests that Samuel House visit New Orleans to check on his wife. #38-588
- James Madison to Mrs. [Nicholas P.] Trist 1786 March 14, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; transcript included. (Box 1)
  #9371-c
- James Madison to Alexander Hamilton 1788 June 25, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #11627
- John Page to James Madison 1788 August 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #7960
- Edmund Randolph to James Madison 1788 November 10, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #4205
- [Justin Pierre Plumard] De Rieux to James Maddison [sic] 1789 February 19, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #9521-e
- James Madison to [Eliza House Trist] [1790] May 27, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #5845-a
- List of Books sent to James Madison by Thomas Jefferson from France, in Madison's hand 1790 August, AD, 3 pp. on 2 l.; Barrow. (Box 1)
- Richard Bland Lee to James Madison 1791 April 17, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l.; with address leaf; docketed; photocopy. Original in Tracy W. McGregor Library Autograph Collection. (Box 1)
  #3684
- James Madison to G[eorge] Jay 1792 May 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; transcript included. (Box 1)
  #4502
- James Madison to his father, Colonel James Madison 1794 June 15, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #7699
- James Madison to James Maury 1797 January 18, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed; photocopy. (Box 1)
  #949
- George S. Washington to James Madison 1800 December 18, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed; copy. (Box 1)
  #317
- F. Brooke to James Madison 1801 April 1, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  Brooke introduces Henry Coleman.
  #8552
- James Madison to William Thornton 1801 April 24, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. with address leaf. (Box 1)
  Madison thanks Thornton for the proffer of hospitality when next in Washington and mentions Thomas Jefferson's recent visit to Virginia.
  #4476
- Richard Peters to James Madison 1801 June 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  Peters thanks Madison for copies of "Robinson's Cases and Strickland's Observations in American Agriculture," comments on the difficulty the printer [James Humphreys] has had in selling the former, criticizes Strickland's work and that of other travelling European "birds of passage" including a "silly book by one Weld" and one by Liancourt that have done "much mischief." He notes that George Washington was often bothered by these traveller's inquiries.
  #10015-j
- J. Ogilvie to James Madison 1801 July 12, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #6564
- A[lbert] Gallatin to James Madison 1801 July 27, ALS, 1 p.; portion cut away from center right. (Box 1)
  #8707
- John G. Jackson to James Madison 1801 August 3, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #8005
- Daniel D'Ogley to James Madison, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- Spencer Roane to James Madison 1801 October 4, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #13314
- Nath[aniel] Irwin to James Madison 1802 January 7, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #10592
- James Madison to [Wilson Cary Nicholas?] 1802 January 25, ALS, fragment. (Box 1)
  #1397
- James Madison to Rufus King 1802 April 7, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #5853
- J[ohn] G. Jackson to James Madison 1802 June 17, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Madison to Isaac Briggs 1802, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; transcript included. (Box 1)
  #5075
- James Madison to Thomas Newton Jr. 1803 July 5, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #5475
- Reuben Beverley to James Madison 1803 August 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- John Madison to James Madison 1803 November 18, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #8933
- James Madison to "Sir" 1803 November [20], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #2474, Tracy W. McGregor Library
- Lewis Deblois to James Madison 1804 January 12, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Madison to [Samuel Latham] Mitchell 1804 January 14, AL, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed (Mitchill); Barrow. (Box 1)
  #3800
- John Madison to James Madison 1804 February 17, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- John Page to James Madison 1804 March 23, ALS, 1 p. (signature cut) with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Madison to L[ittleton] W. Tazewell 1804 May 4, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #4950
- James Madison to Tench Coxe 1804 May 8, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked. (Box 1)
  #1595
- [Mr. and Mrs. Pechon] to James Madison 1804 August 27, AL, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Madison to Fulwar Skipwith 1804 November 10, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- William Eaton to James Madison 1805 March 4, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box 1)
  #3070-d
- James Madison to William Billings 1805 March 12, LS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #2237
- Lewis DeBlois to James Madison 1805 June 28, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- J[oseph] H[amilton] Daveiss 1805 December 20, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box 1)
  #11128
- James Madison to "Sidi Suliman Melli Melli" [Soliman Melemini] 1806 February 4, L, 5 pp. on 4 l., with additional blank leaf; 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  "No.2"
  #9737-a
- "Sidi Suliman Melli Melli" [Soliman Melemini] to James Madison 1806 February 10, L, 2 pp. on 1 l.; 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  "No.3 "
- James Madison to [Melli Melli] 1806 March 4, LS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  "No.4"
- "Sidi Suliman Melli Melli" [Soliman Melemini] to James Madison 1806 February 11, L, 5 pp. on 4 l., with additional blank leaf; 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  "No.5"
- James Madison to "Sidi Suliman Melli Melli" [Soliman Melemini] 1806 March 17, L, 5 pp. on 1 l.; 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  "No.6"
- "Sidi Suliman Melli Melli" [Soliman Melemini] to James Madison 1806 March 18, L, 4 pp. on 4 l.; 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  "No.7"
- James Madison to "Sidi Suliman Melli Melli" [Soliman Melemini] 1806 March 31, L, 2 pp. on 1 l.; 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  "No.8"
- James Madison to Mrs. D. Stewart 1806 May 20, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #4831
- James Madison to "Jussuf Hoggia" 1806 March 31, L, 2 pp. on 1 l.; 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  "No.9"
- James Madison to James Breckinridge 1806 December 27, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; transcript included. (Box 1)
  #10395
- James Madison to [James] Fenner 1807 January 30, AL, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #4013
- F[erdinando] Fairfax to James Madison 1807 March 21, ALS, 1 p.; trimmed, with portion cut from lower left; docketed. (Box 1)
- J[ohn] G. Jackson to James Madison 1807 March 26, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- James Madison to Joseph Prentis 1807 June 3, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box 1)
  #4136
- James Madison to Isaac Chauncey 1807 June 15, LS, 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #5504
- J[ohn] G. Jackson to James Madison 1807 November 8, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
  #4158
- J[ohn] G. Jackson to James Madison 1808 February 4, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- Robert Brent to James Madison 1808 February 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #7617
- Richard Forrest to [James Madison] 1808 May 8, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- Richard Forrest to James Madison 1808 August 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- William Lee to James Madison 1808 June 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Meriwether Lewis, bill of exchange to James Madison 1809 February 6, ADS, 2 pp. on 2 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #9041
- Louis Dubois to [James Madison] 1809 March 5, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
- Richard Forrest to James Madison 1809 July 7, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
- Richard Forrest to James Madison 1809 August 27, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Madison to Mr. Nicholson 1810 February 22, AN, 1 p.; with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 1)
- James M. Henry to James Madison 1810 June 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 1)
- James Madison to Mrs. Elizabeth Trist 1810 July 25, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf.; silked. (Box 1)
  #38-588
- William Lee to James Madison 1810 August 8, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- Richard Forrest to James Madison 1810 August 15, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- Richard Forrest to James Madison 1810 September 14, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 1)
- Richard Forrest to James Madison 1810, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Carpenter's bills for work on Montpelier for James Madison 1810-1812, D, 4 items (13 pp. on 8 l.); Barrow. (Box 1)
  #5680
- James Madison, Commission to Joseph Prentis as Inspector of the Revenue 1811 February 19, ADS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- James Madison, Commission to Joseph Prentis as Surveyor 1811 February 19, ADS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- Phoebe Morris to James Madison "for Mrs. Madison" 1811 May 6, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. Transcript included. (Box 1)
  #3940-a
- James Madison Fragment 1812 January 15, TDS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #2723
- Richard Bland Lee to James Madison 1812 January 16, ALS, 3 pp. on 3 l.; with address leaf; docketed; photocopy. Original in Tracy W. McGregor Library autograph collection. (Box 1)
- James Madison to [Anthony Charles] Cazenove 1812 April 2, ALS, 1 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #13827
- William [Cobbett?] to James Madison 1812 June 12, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  Recommendation for Asbury Dickins to replace General Lyman as Consul in Great Britain.
  #5533-c
- "Extracts from the Exposition of the Political Jesuitism of James Madison by an Observant Citizen of the District of Columbia" [1812], AMS, 30 pp. on 9 l. (Box 1)
  #9737-b
- James Madison to [?] 1813 January 4, ALS, 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #1398, 1232
- J[ohn] G. Jackson to James Madison 1813 April 19, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
- James Madison to [?] (Draft of Letter) [1813 September 13], ANS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- Henry Clay to [James Madison] [1813 December 11], ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. (Box 1)
  #991
- R.L. Madison to James Madison [1814] March 19, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Document Signed by James Madison and James Monroe 1814 January 12, DS, 1 p. Duplicate. (Box 1)
  #8627
- James Madison to Thomas Morris 1814 [post June 27], ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- James Madison to Peter Hagner [ca.1814], AN, 1 p.; draft (Box 1)
  #14241,
- Appointment of De La Fayette Johnston 1815 April 15, ADS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #4535
- Appointment of De La Fayette Johnston 1815 April 20, ADS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- Invitation to Mr. [Joseph] Nourse to dinner 1815 June 20, AN, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #3490-a
- Pardon of John Crowley 1815 September 11, ADS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #2257
- Richard Bland Lee to James Madison 1816 April 27, ALS, 3 pp. on 3 l.; with address leaf; photocopy. Original in Tracy W. McGregor Library autograph collection. (Box 1)
- James Madison to unidentified recipient 1816 April, AL, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #14241
- Richard Bland Lee to [James Madison] 1816 May 6, ALS, 1 p.; photocopy. Original in Tracy W. McGregor Library autograph collection. (Box 1)
- [?] to James Madison 1816 June 6, ALS, 1 p.; Translation from French to English included. (Box 1)
- James Madison to [Wilson Cary Nicholas] 1816 December 10, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
- N. G. Dufres to James Madison 1816 December 20, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box 1)
- Thomas Cooper to James Madison 1816 December 24, ANS, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #6858
- William H. Murfee to James Madison 1816 December 31, AN, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
- Christian Neale to James Madison 1817 February 5, ALS, 1 p. (Box 1)
- N.G. Dufres to James Madison 1817 March 17, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box 1)
- James Madison to Charles F. Mercer 1817 August, ALS, 1 p. with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #7932
- James Madison to Richard Cutts 1817 October 12, ALS, 2 pp.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 1)
  #2288
- Thomas Cooper to James Madison 1817 November 24, ALS, 2 pp.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 1)
  #13684
- James Madison to Joseph Cabell 1818 February 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #4645, Tracy W. McGregor Library
- James Madison to W[illiam] Lee 1818 March 5, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
  #9371-d
- James Madison to [David] Watson 1818 January 3, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf, docketed; silked. (Box 2)
  Madison encloses a letter from Thomas Jefferson [not present] to the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia and asks Watson to sign it and send it on to "General [John Hartwell] Cocke." #14799
- James Madison to [James Barbour] 1818 April 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box 2)
- James Madison to [Richard] Cutts 1818 July 27, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #1661, Tracy W. McGregor Library
- [James Madison] to [Thomas Jefferson] [1818 October], L, 1 p. (fragment); photocopy. Original in the Thomas Jefferson Papers. (Box 2)
  #10347
- James Madison to William Logan 1819 August 12, AL, (draft) 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #5536
- James Madison to [Richard Cutts] 1818 November 25, ALS, 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 2)
- James Madison to James Breckinridge 1819 December 8, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Madison to Benjamin Silliman 1820 May 25, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
  #2803, Tracy W. McGregor Library
- James Madison to Chapman Reynolds 1820 July 24, ANS, 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #6078
- James Madison to Joseph Delaplaine 1820 October, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
- Andrew Stevenson to James Madison 1820 December 3, ALS, 1 p.
  #8481
- James Madison to Governor Brown 1821 February 15, AL, 1 p. (Box 2)
  #5487
- James Madison to [Spencer Roane] 1821 May 6, ALS, 7 pp. on 2 l. (Box 2)
  #1714-b
- James Madison to James Bruce 1821 October 20, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box 2)
  #2692
- James Madison to Dolley Madison 1821 November 30, ALS, 1 p.; docketed; Transcript. (Box 2)
  #12074
- James Madison to J.G. Jackson 1821 December 28, ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l.; with address leaf; with extracts from letter of 1821 September 15 (2 pp. on 1 l.); silked. Transcript and photocopy included. (Box 2)
  #6570
- Richard Forrest to James Madison 1822 April 25, ALS, 2 pp.; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
- Richard Forrest to James Madison 1822 May 11, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. (Box 2)
- Robert C. Foster to James Madison 1822 June 22, ALS, 2 pp.; docketed. (Box 2)
- Thomas Ritchie to James Madison 1822 August 7, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Madison to Jed Morse 1823 March 28, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #8347
- James Madison to Joseph C. Cabell 1823 May 10, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #38-111 from Cabell Deposit
- James Madison to "Dear Sir" 1823 August 23, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #10464
- F.W. Hatch to James Madison 1823 November 3, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
- James Madison to Reverend Frederick Beasley 1823 November 24, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; negative photocopy. (Box 2)
  #5506-a
- Robert C. Foster to James Madison 1824 January 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Madison to Richard Rush 1824 April 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; silked. (Box 2)
- Address by James Madison 1824 April 24, AD, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #1813
- James Madison to Thomas Jefferson 1824 October 9, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; docketed by T.J.; photocopy, original in Jefferson Papers. (Box 2)
  #12181
- James Madison's Toast to Lafayette at Orange C.H. 1824 November 25, AD, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box 2)
  #4677
- James Madison to Joel Poinsett 1824 December 10, ALS, 1 p.; Barrow. (Box 2)
- James Madison to Reverend Frederick Beasley 1824 December 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l.; negative photocopy. (Box 2)
- James Madison to [Joseph C. Cabell] 1825 April 13, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
  #38-111
- James Madison to Asbury Dickens 1825 July 19, ALS, 1 p.; mounted. (Box 2)
  #11201-a
- James Madison, Montpellier to [Thomas Jefferson] 1825 August 4., ALS. 1 pp. Endorsed by T. J. (Box 2)
  Discusses qualifications of John Tayloe Lomax for the Professorship of Law at the University of Virginia as relayed by Judge Barbour. #14476
- James Madison to Joseph C. Cabell 1826 January 26, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #2529
- James Madison to John Payne Todd 1826 February 15, AL, 1 p. (Box 2)
- James Madison to Littleton D. Teakle 1826 March 29, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf. (Box 2)
  #2338
- James Madison to Martin Van Buren 1826 April 28, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
  #4888
- Promissory note signed by James Madison 1826 May 10, ANS, 1 p.; upper left corner of text torn away; Barrow. (Box 2)
- Sight draft to Richard Rush for refund of duty paid on marble imported for the University of Virginia 1826 October 5, ANS, 2 pp. (Box 2)
  #5517
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett 1826 October 24, ANS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked. (Box 2)
  #860
- James Madison to John Hartwell Cocke 1826 November 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #1480
- James Madison to Presidential Board of Directors of the Literary Fund 1826 November 24, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #3351
- James Madison to [Dolley Madison] 1826 December 4, ALS, 1 p. (Box 2)
- James Madison to W.S. Nicholls, Esq. December 22, 1826, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; portion of left margin torn away, affecting text; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #9551
- James Madison to John Hartwell Cocke 1826 December 27, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #3184
- [James Madison] to N. P. Trist 1827 January 12, AL fragment, 2 pp. on 1 l.; Barrow. (Box 2)
- James Madison to Joseph C. Cabell 1827 January 13, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with address leaf; docketed; Barrow. (Box 2)
- James Madison to Alexander Garrett 1827 January 17, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked. (Box 2)
- James Madison to John Hartwell Cocke 1827 January 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l.; second leaf partial. (Box 2)
  #640 (1480)
- James Madison to Arthur Brockenbrough 1827 January 23, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; Barrow. (Box 2)
  #2737, 3730
- James Madison to Joseph C. Cabell 1827 February 7, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Madison to [John Hartwell] Cocke 1827 February 12, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
- James Madison to William Matthews [1827] February 13, ALS, 1 p.; with address leaf; docketed; silked. (Box 2)
  #RG-1/3/3.804
- James Madison to John Hartwell Cocke 1827 March 18, LS, 3 pp. on 2 l.; copy in unidentified hand; with address leaf; docketed. (Box 2)
  #640
- James Madison to [John Hartwell] Cocke 1827 March 26, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. (Box 2)